With a population of 14 million,
Kinshasa is the largest French-speaking city in the world.
The streets are full of activity.
Many people get up very early,
at around 5 a.m.,
and take on several jobs during the day to get by.
Africa News,
Palmares,
Machete,
Le Fas,
Referance.
They can be couriers.
Sweepers,
maggot sellers,
or even jewelers.
At midday,
they count their money,
often dreaming of making a fortune.
They even dream of wealth in this slum,
like 80%
of its inhabitants.
Albert,
a fisherman,
lives on less than £1.50 per day.
The country's richest people live just opposite him.
That's La Cité du Fleuve
They are rich, and we are poor.
They are doing business, we are fishing.
This apartment complex is reserved for the new upper class,
and of course the millionaires of the Democratic Republic of Congo.
It's impossible for anyone from the outside to get in.
Fale Ipupa is one of these hugely wealthy people that the rest of the country dreams of becoming.
Never in my wildest dream when I was a kid could
I have imagined having cars and all these things.
Just from singing, and being recognised
in Kinshasa and then all over Africa.
Fale Ipupa is the most famous singer in the Democratic Republic of Congo.
He performs all over the world with international stars,
and he is a multi-millionaire.
uidas
adidas
Guy,
I love you,
man.
I love you too.
My love,
Fally Pupa,
you know.
What you saying?
Hey.
He has just invested over 600,000 pounds for his new home in this Riverside estate.
Are the doors open?
Go on, open them!
I really like being here, especially on Sundays.
It's relaxing.
I love our river and I come here often with friends
and family, so I decided to lay a few bricks.
Just a few bricks makes this Californian-style villa,
which stands out hugely here in the Congo,
the eighth poorest country in the world.
His neighbors are lawyers,
financiers,
or entrepreneurs.
who have made their fortune selling raw materials,
which the rest of the world is snapping up.
The Congo's underground reserves are full of wealth and boost the economy.
These people are very wealthy.
They could live in London or Miami,
but they've chosen to stay here.
That's good.
Folly likes to relax far away from the hustle and bustle of the city center.
The Congo River,
one of the longest in the world,
is the city's playground.
But it's also a source of livelihood for fishermen,
who have quickly recognized him.
Fally! Please can you help us at all?
They say they're my brothers, they want
a bit of money, I have to give it to them.
Give them 50 dollars.
Fali gets a port employee to distribute a few notes among them.
That's a lot. We shouted Fally, Fally, and he
gave us 50 dollars to share between us six.
It's the equivalent of six pounds per fisherman,
which is the same as an entire working week.
These people have different problems from us.
They even work on Sundays and if I have
the opportunity to give a little something...
...even if it's just so that they can take
something home for their children...
I will always be happy to do it.
The Democratic Republic of Congo is the largest country in Central Africa.
It's four times the size of France.
It has been ravaged repeatedly by war for almost
60 years,
which has resulted in over 6 million deaths.
The country is also under a dictatorship.
Mobutu Seziseko,
nicknamed the Leopard of Zaire,
was in power for 32 years.
While ruling the country with an iron fist,
he embezzled 4 billion pounds.
In 1996,
a civil war broke out.
Militias supported by neighboring countries enlisted thousands of child soldiers to try and seize the country's wealth.
Mobutu,
meanwhile,
eventually died in exile.
Another emblematic president in the early
2000s was Joseph Kabila.
He accumulated more than 11 billion pounds during his 18 years in power.
He returned to power in January 2019.
Today,
entire regions are still unstable in this huge country.
Everything still needs to be built,
and some businessmen make their fortune amid this chaos.
In the Congo, you can wake up
poor in the morning...
...and become rich the following day
because you have worked.
Eric has a huge project at the end of this extremely dangerous road.
He is erecting a huge dam to provide the population with electricity.
It's going to bring in almost
one million dollars per month.
In the east of the country,
the Great Lakes region is one of its most beautiful areas,
but also one of the most dangerous in Africa,
having been in almost permanent war for over 20 years.
Robert,
a former rebel leader,
has become a businessman.
He is also a politician.
When you're a member of parliament,
politics doesn't stop us from doing business.
Robert built his fortune in coltan mines.
This is an essential ore for the manufacturing of mobile phones.
A small town has been created thanks to this businessman's employment.
And every day,
3,000 miners also dream of a better life.
When I see this car, I tell myself that I could have
one like that some day, if God grants me the means.
The Congo's underground wealth has really boosted the economy.
An upper class is emerging,
and in Kinshasa,
the capital,
new products are appearing.
This orange juice costs almost 20 pounds.
But the majority of the population is still extremely poor.
With such disadvantage,
these people find refuge in religion,
which provides a windfall for corrupt pastors,
who have practically become stars by selling miracle cures at a high price.
This cures many diseases, even AIDS.
We have traveled to one of the most chaotic countries in Africa to understand how its people managed to get by,
and sometimes even managed to build huge fortunes.
In Kinshasa,
the roads resemble like battered tracks.
They're difficult to navigate.
In this huge mess,
a young woman is fighting for her future.
She is called Mukembe.
They are law enforcement officers, we are
supposed to follow what they say...
Yet here I am in front of two officers,
one who is telling me to go to the left...
and the other to go to the right.
What am I supposed to do?
Boukembe is in the middle of a test.
Sat in the back,
Arnaud must evaluate her ability to sneak through traffic and put a bit of pressure on her.
After you turn again, take a right here.
You don't know the road apparently.
Turn left, go ahead, follow the car.
Gokhebi has applied for a job as a driver in a start-up company.
The company was created by a Congolese businesswoman who wants to lift women out of poverty and is recognizable by its pink cars.
Okembe was a nurse until this point.
If she passes the test,
she will triple her salary,
raising it to 200 pounds per month.
can't wait to start my job, let's hope
it's all gone OK and I've passed the test.
We will go around and then go back to the office.
To give herself the best chance,
Mukambi stays in character right until the end.
But it will be a few days until she finds out if she has got the right person.
There are already about 15 cars in the company's car park.
The startup wants to create high-end services for the middle and upper class.
There are drinks,
cakes,
and even a Wi-Fi connection to allow clients to work while they sit in Kinshasa's traffic jams.
You don't find things like that around here.
We have come up with it.
Patricia is a businesswoman who wants to promote female integration.
After studying in South Africa,
she returned to the Congo.
She has created her driver's service with the help of investors.
She also supports new businesses.
We want to have millionaires.
The Congo is rich.
We have more than 80 million people living here,
we have resources above and below ground...
...and it's time for Congolese women
to take advantage of this wealth.
Despite the instability all over her country...
Give me both, yes two thighs.
Patricia wants to show the whole world that the Democratic Republic of Congo can take off.
The Congo can't be reduced to rapes and wars.
No, there are young people, young women like us
who are trying to make a change...
So it's wrong that people reduce the Congo
to a place where 'things do not work...
things don't evolve' no, it's this new generation
who are going to improve the country.
Just like Patricia and her friends who are banking on the future of their country,
many Congolese people return to work and invest in their country after years of living abroad,
especially in Europe or the United States.
These repatriates,
as they are called,
live in secure areas where they can find all of the comforts that they were used to abroad.
At La Cité de Fleuve,
the complex of high-end apartment buildings and villas extend over 300 hectares and two new people are moving in.
Olivier and Naomi.
A few days ago they were still living in Johannesburg,
South Africa.
The washing machine is really the number
one priority, right darling? And the bed!
Olivier and Naomi work in finance.
They decided to return to their country because there are new professional activities.
The living room will go there, a small
living room, a small living room...
And a carpet there, a table, and a TV.
That's our room.
And it has a breathtaking view of the Congo River.
Olivier and Naomi got married in Kinshasa just three days ago,
and they want to start their family here.
The couple earn 3,000 pounds a month,
which is over 100 times the average.
The rental loan costs almost 1,000 pounds,
but that's the price you pay for security.
I'm in a place where my kids can play in the street,
The project has already successfully passed all of the feasibility tests.
and they don't have to worry about a hundred other people on the street,
and they don't have to worry about air pollution,
noise pollution.
They can do their homework in peace.
So it's also very much about the environment,
but also,
yes,
it is a whole lot safer than the inner city.
We have a brand new spotless apartment..
...we will have brand new appliances and I'm
waiting for my little one who will also be new!
Olivier and Naomi have found their safe haven.
Beginning of a new life for us.
Yes.
Demand to live in this new residence is growing.
Eventually,
La Cité du Fleuve will have more than 2,000 homes,
including that of the singer Fali'i Poupas.
We find him in a large house,
which he has rented as the backdrop of his new music video.
2, 1, 0 Action!
The extras are dressed up as Congolese warriors.
The day starts well for Fali,
but all of a sudden,
the music stops,
for there has been a power cut in the area.
There's no electricity, we are trying
to manage it to see what we can do.
Fali and his team are stuck.
Finally,
A technician manages to get his hands on a generator,
but that quickly breaks down too.
Folly is desperate,
even though he is used to such disappointment.
Look, I'm Congolese, that's to say,
I was born and raised here...
So we cannot leave the country
just because there are power cuts.
Manon,
Falehipupa's assistant,
uses the car's sound system to finish filming the clip.
We make it all with tiny budgets. We will connect
it to the car while we wait for the current.
We have no choice.
Thanks to this trick,
shooting can finish without a hitch.
In his 20-year career,
Folly has earned several million pounds.
He has had a huge success,
which is not necessarily an anomaly in this country.
Congo's underground is rich in minerals,
which have helped make the fortune of several well-advised men.
One of the main resources is coltan.
which,
once it's been transformed,
is used in the manufacturing of mobile phones.
The mines are in the Great Lakes region,
in the east of the country,
on the Rwandan border.
In Goma,
the capital of North Kivu,
conflicts have been raging for over 20 years.
Armed groups are trying to seize the land's wealth.
The UN permanently deploys 16,000 peacekeepers to maintain a semblance of peace in the region.
The region is very poor,
traumatized by successive rebellions and massacres.
Those who have made their fortune,
especially in raw materials,
live in the luxurious Lake Kivu.
One of the region's most important businessmen lives in this huge villa.
There is a watchtower with a huge police presence at the entrance.
It's a true fortress.
Its owner has several tens of millions of pounds.
How are you, François?
sir.
Robert Seninga is the king of the Coltan mines.
He has had an eventful life.
Formerly,
he was a rebel leader.
Today,
he is a businessman and also a member of the Maissi Parliament,
a district near Tagoma.
When you're a politician, politics
doesn't stop you from doing business.
He even admits that his power has helped him to become an owner of some of these mines.
Robert Seninga is also the president of one of the largest corporations extracting Clotin in this region.
He is always escorted by armed guards as he regularly receives threats.
Where are we?
This is the corporation's headquarters.
This is the head office.
This is where the trading takes place.
The building does not pay for the mine,
but the cooperative earns millions in turnover every year.
Hello, how are you?
Robert Seninga gives an update on coltan production over the last few days.
On the 6th, we got 4 tons 668 kilos in total.
And the numbers are pretty good.
We are swimming in 40 tons.
And so what's the revenue on that?
A kilo is 42-45 dollars.
You have the figure, you have the figure...
Robert Seninga prefers to remain discreet.
These last few days,
the mines have given a lot to the cooperative and to their owners,
almost 2 million pounds.
The businessman employs 3,000 people to achieve these results.
He claims to be a faultless boss.
Are there any children working in your mines?
ayama bwiriza
lyi ndiyo namna inayo kubungabunga
Are there any'children working in your mines?
Are there any children working in your mines?
imba madini
No, there are no children because it's forbidden.
There are officers who are responsible for ensuring
that children do not end up in there.
Children should be in school, not the mines.
Helmets,
boots,
and masks are mandatory in the mines to ensure the workers'
safety.
In fact,
the site could be a model example for the region.
These mines are situa-
It's 60 kilometers from Goma in a beautiful region of North Kivu with hills and pastures as far as the eye can see.
It is also one of the most dangerous regions in Africa.
It has been at war for over 25 years.
In 1995,
one of the worst tragedies of the 20th century broke out in Rwanda.
A genocide which would kill almost one million people.
Hundreds of thousands of survivors fled to the neighboring Democratic Republic of Congo,
and North Kivu in particular.
But militants who took part in the massacre joined the exodus.
Since then,
this region in the east of the Congo has been extremely volatile.
Dozens of rebel groups are clashing,
and in particular,
they are trying to capture some of the Congolese underground wealth.
Landry Robertseninga's chief engineer accompanies us to his mines.
Seninga has saved the local community, Maisi,
because thanks to him, life can go on as normal.
Yet little seems to have changed in the region in recent years.
The road is in a terrible state.
Every day,
people risk their lives in order to work.
Our car struggles to get to the ravine,
despite several attempts due to crevices full of water.
We were seconds away!
Otherwise we would have ended up in this river
and had been in serious trouble.
Fatal
accidents are common on this road.
Nice, we've been saved!
It will take us a total of five hours to travel just 60 kilometers.
We've arrived.
This is Rubaiya,
a town near the mining site.
The town has boomed recently,
growing exponentially in just a few years.
Today,
10,000 people live here,
practically cut off from the outside world.
Life is organized.
There's a sewing workshop,
a hairdresser's,
and even something that's turned its inside into a nightclub.
In Robaya,
everything has been created to meet the needs of the population that has come to take advantage of this new Congolese wild west.
Robert Seninga's face is displayed everywhere.
According to Landry,
his loyal follower,
he can make all dreams possible.
Here is where the first miner lived.
He was the first person to start working in
the first hole that was discovered in Rubaya.
He managed to build this beautiful house
which you see here.
miracle seems to be taking place.
But upon closer look,
most homes are simple wooden shacks.
Jou lives here with his wife and their three children.
With five people living in 15 square meters of space,
they are forced to be very tidy.
The house is very small.
We hang the shoes on the wall.
And we put the children's clothes over there.
In the other room,
the kitchen is attached to the family bed.
The bed is really small.
We sleep there and my wife cooks here.
The couple moved here five years ago,
when Gilles wanted to earn his fortune in the mines.
When I see this car I tell myself that I
could have one like that one day...
...if God granted me the means to do so.
For now,
Gilles only earns five euros per day.
He works 10 kilometers from the center of Urbaya and must travel for an hour and a half to get there.
Hundreds of coltan extraction sites surround the area.
Jiz is called Bamfu.
Every day,
it filters Khotan mixed with sand that is extracted from the mine.
It's easier to sort the coltan by hand,
so we are able to separate it from the sand.
Coltan is this black substance.
Once transformed,
it goes into the manufacturing of micro-electronic components.
That's the coltan.
That's what goes into mobile phones.
Later on,
Jill has to go into the mine to dig.
The wall is very slippery.
Wait.
Stop!
Going down isn't difficult if you look after yourself.
And there's no safety measure to rely on along this
15-meter descent.
Once you've arrived at the bottom,
it is difficult to breathe.
Tons of sand have already been extracted,
which has opened up tunnels.
There is no supporting structure to secure them.
so the risk of a landslide is very high.
Zhiyu extracts the coltan using just his hands.
There is a lot of sand here. It's endless.
There's really a lot.
Priority is given to extraction,
never safety.
There are regular accidents in these mines.
It's very dangerous to be here, right?
It's brittle but it's well-developed.
But Landry,
our guide,
doesn't see the problem.
In Rubaya mines and wherever we work..
.there are cases where we have recorded deaths, case
...cases of landslides, and that's
why there can be deaths.
Imagine if this thing rushed towards us
like that, we would suffocate.
There are some who can resist
and others who cannot.
There are no official figures,
but men regularly lose their lives extracting Clotin.
How old are you?
I'm twenty years old.
He's twenty years old,
you can see him...
Here, you can see that he's thin.
I can see why someone might think that
he's too young, but he is paid for his work.
Auger's 30 or so colleagues,
at least half,
don't seem to be older than teenagers.
This site isn't an anomaly.
We meet a lot of children in the region who hide from the camera.
According to UNICEF,
mines allegedly employ 40,000 children.
This mineral,
which is generating fortunes,
steals these children's childhood and sometimes even their lives.
Two months before filming,
a massacre took place one evening in the center of Rubaya.
Three men armed with machetes launched an attack.
Twelve were killed,
including three women and a five-year-old child.
It was undoubtedly a settling of scores over the Khotan black market that plagues the region.
Underground reselling of Khotan happens at all levels of the production chain,
from miners to site managers.
Much of the product is sold illegally to avoid paying taxes to the Congolese government.
In Goma,
we pose as traders wanting to buy smuggled Khotan.
We made an appointment with traffickers.
Do you want one ton, two tons, three tons?
It depends on the price.
That's not a problem.
The traffickers present us with different coltan samples to try and convince us.
Where does that one come from, Masisi?
- Yes, Masisi.
Where exactly?
- Rubaya.
According to these sellers,
the coltan comes from the place where we just left.
90 dollars per kilo?
- Yes.
This Khloetan is tax-free.
At this price,
the traffickers are responsible for delivering the goods across the Rwandan border.
The country is regularly accused of stimulating economic growth through smuggled raw materials from the Democratic Republic of Congo.
This theft takes place with the help of Congolese soldiers.
Like this man,
who lets the convoys pass through.
Do you see coltan passing through every day?
Some days 2, 3, or even 10 tons
can pass through.
Like all Congolese civil servants,
this soldier only gets a small salad.
With coltan, I can easily earn 1000 dollars a day
So everyone does it.
Yes.
If traffickers come and offer me 500 or 1000 dollars
I can't refuse.
I earn 80 dollars a month, so when I have the option
of getting 1000 dollars a day, it's an easy decision.
The DRC is one of the 20 most corrupt countries on the planet.
In total,
corruption costs the Congolese state 11 billion pounds every year.
Despite all of this trafficking,
the mining sector drives the DRC's economy.
The country's economy has grown by almost a quarter.
by almost 6%
in 2018,
thanks to this industry.
This economic success is showcased in Kinshasa,
the capital,
around the Boulevard d'Outre-Jouan.
The 30th of June is their Independence Day,
which was granted after almost a century of Belgian rule.
Here in the business district we find Olivier,
the young banker who moved to the Cité du Fleuve a few weeks ago with his wife Naomi.
A cheesecake?
Yes, I love them.
Yes, I love them too, or apple pie?
9.350fc Yes, I love them too, or apple pie?
They didn't exist when I was a kid.
These pastries cost four pounds each,
the same price as in the UK.
They're a luxury in Kinshasa.
5950 FC.
That's 27.78 dollars please.
21 pounds is almost the country's average salary,
but that doesn't seem to bother Olivier.
It's cheap, it's fine.
Although these well-paid executives only make up a tiny part of the population,
new businesses are slowly but surely being set up in the city center.
No, this isn't the one we usually use.
This supermarket has adapted its stock.
From coffee capsules to European cheeses to cereal,
you can find everything here that is sold in rich countries.
Okay,
so we go.
Yeah.
Can we get a...
Juice.
But they have to pay a huge price for all of these imported products.
$31,000.
How many dollars?
That's about
$20. It's too expensive for anyone really.
I can't speak for other people,
but...
No,
for you.
$20 is expensive for me.
I wouldn't spend a can of mayonnaise.
Most of the imported products are very expensive.
A four-pack of yogurts comes to almost eight pounds.
A box of cereal is ten pounds.
That's three times more expensive than in the UK.
You know the perception that people have of them?
Yeah.
When they hear of Congo,
they think war,
they think the jungle,
civilized people.
This type of supermarket in the city
is attracting more and more well-off clients,
as well as those who have lived abroad,
like Olivier and Naomi.
I can't imagine myself going to the market,
because that's the first thing I thought when I was a kid.
I thought,
oh,
my gosh,
when I live on my own,
I need to start going to the market and buying things,
you know,
in the flea market and whatnot.
But,
yeah,
if this didn't exist,
I don't know if we'd eat.
Naomi makes sure that she eats about about
balanced diet because she is pregnant.
It will be a boy.
He's due in three months.
It's a baby boy.
I'm a little bit nervous,
but happy at the same time.
I think it's just like first time parents.
We've never raised another human before.
This is the perfect outcome for the couple who have had time to settle down.
Thank you.
I think we're done.
Little by little,
their apartment is becoming more homely.
Heavenly Father,
thank you for this meal.
We thank you for this.
This meal gives them a chance to consider their child's future,
which will most likely be in the Democratic Republic of Congo.
If he wants to become a doctor, we now
have the money to pay for his medical studies.
If he wants to become a sportsman...
...we will have enough money to put him in
an academy to do football or basketball...
Why?
Because I want him to be his own boss.
And I don't want him to spend his life working for somebody else.
An entrepreneur,
the job that young Congolese people dream of.
The job is demanding,
but the success more than makes up for it.
This evening,
an entrepreneur is celebrating an exciting new contract.
He is called Eric Monga.
This business leader is also at the top of an employer's union.
Let's toast to the future of our business...
And the future success of your company.
Eric's friends are drinking only the best champagne.
They are celebrating good news.
The businessman has just come back from Florida in the USA,
where he met with investors.
He is in the process of convincing them to fund his project,
which is certainly ambitious.
and which will cost upwards of
He has negotiated a contract which has
gone through which I cannot disclose here.
However, I can tell you that the contract
our friend just negotiated...
...is worth drinking a glass of champagne for.
Eric wants to construct what will be one of the Congo's largest dams.
Today,
less than one in five Congolese people are connected to the electricity network.
Eric is hoping to fill part of this gap with this new project.
For every problem we face, there is
a business opportunity that comes with it.
People must eat, they must get dressed and now,
we want to give electricity to the people next year.
In time,
Eric will improve the living conditions for some of his 81 million fellow citizens.
The businessman is from Lumbumbashi in the south of the Congo.
He has made his fortune by creating a company specializing in the analysis of minerals.
The entrepreneur is leaving this morning for an expedition on the site of his future dam.
Hey Isaac, let's go!
It is 350 kilometers away.
Eric is looking to check the river's flow rate.
But the road is extremely dangerous,
and Eric asks his colleagues to be careful.
We are waiting for you in Kalera.
Don't forget that you have to make
the journey during the day.
You wouldn't want to drive at night.
There are no lights,
very little signage,
and potholes everywhere.
The National Road 1 highway,
which crosses Katanga,
is one of the most deadly roads in the country.
Many lorries transporting minerals and chemical products used in the mining industry use this road every day.
Acid, acid, acid.
Drivers on this road will take any risks necessary to ensure timely delivery of their precious merchandise.
Roads in the Congo are deadly,
there are a lot of accidents.
There are some crazy drivers.
Three of the 11 passengers in this vehicle were just killed just a few hours ago.
But that doesn't affect these drivers.
Eric is worried.
A high-speed car suddenly comes by a little too close.
What's going on?
There is a man behind me who wants to overtake
but he's crazy...
He's being really impatient
and putting me in danger.
Despite the low visibility,
the driver goes for it.
It looks like he is fleeing the police.
It's just a small spat but he's got nothing to
gain other than putting our lives in danger...
After three hours of difficult driving,
Eric can finally breathe a sigh of relief.
He leaves the National Road 1 highway to take a long
100-kilometer track,
which is used far less frequently.
The area where he hopes to
to set up his dam is currently very remote.
In order to construct it,
he will have to bring workers in from far away.
But the challenge is worth it.
It's going to earn me almost 1 million
dollars per month, it's a nice paycheck!
And that...
Oh, sorry, that's the ditch!
In the meantime,
Eric has set up a small camp in the middle of nowhere,
which hosts a dozen engineers.
Hello.
Is everything ok here?
The employees have been living here for a year completely alone.
They have a water tank,
a generator and a small shed for tools.
When does the sun set here?
At around 6:15.
So we still have 40 minutes,
I really need to see the water level today.
Despite being tired from traveling,
this businessman can't waste any time.
He leads his team to the bank of the Lofira River,
which runs through the dam.
Eric checks the height and the speed of the water.
And how much did you say it was there?
The water level is 1 metre 63.
1 metre 63 compared to the scale over there.
The project has already successfully passed all of the feasibility tests.
We are at around 735 metres
and the dam will be 830 metres.
The water will stop at the first level there,
almost on the edge of the horizon over there...
...that will all be a lake.
The project will be one of the five largest in the Congo.
With a height of 90 meters,
it will produce 150 megawatts of power,
which we'll be able to use to power the entire Congo.
to provide 500,000 people with electricity.
It will supply the equivalent of the population of Manchester.
The dam's construction is expected to create almost 3,000 jobs and boost the region's economy.
We are constructing something permanent
and which will serve an entire community..
.bringing joy for all of the locals who
just needed this energy in order to develop.
Several large investors, notably american’s
have registered their interest in the project.
Eric hopes to gather the 250 million pounds needed for the project in the next three years.
Upon returning to the camp,
he has a small surprise for his team.
We have a saying here that goes 'Koutoumba
and buouavakila' which means 'drink and talk!'
He has asked his cook to prepare a celebratory meal of traditional dishes.
That's Ngai Ngai grown in Boiri.
It's very close to here.
These are amaranths...
Also grown in Boiri.
Thank you.
Eric believes that in this country,
one of the least developed in the world,
there are various opportunities for success.
You just need to dare to take a leap and get started.
We have seen a lot of people coming to the Congo...
.going to where it's difficult, where there's
nothing and succeeding. And why can't I?
That's the Congo...
You can wake up poor and the next day,
you will be rich because you have worked hard.
Inspired by the boldness and success of entrepreneurs like Eric,
more and more Congolese people are throwing themselves into the world of business in a hope to escape poverty.
And this dream motivates thousands of women in Kinshasa every day.
They come at 4 a.m.
from all parts of the city to stock up on bread from this wholesaler.
They buy whatever they can to make a living that day.
Marie comes here every day for the 6 a.m.
batch.
I'll take two tubs.
Marie was widowed six months ago and therefore has the huge responsibility of bringing enough home to feed her whole family.
Wait, give me that please.
It's not too heavy for me, I'm used
to carrying it all, it's my job.
Marie is carrying more than 15 kilograms of goods on her head.
She sets up her stall in a strategic location every day,
which will get her the most clients.
I'll have a cake.
How much is it?
The cake is 300 francs.
- Ok, I will take one.
I am going to give you two.
I'll give you two because you're a little thin.
Oh, thank you very much.
I just bought some bread from Marie
because I pass by her stand.
I really like it, it's clean and she
takes good care of her stand.
Thanks to her smile and her kindness,
Marie usually attracts a lot of customers.
It's a good day, it's going well!
Marie earns 50 pounds per day,
thanks to this little stand.
She believes in her business and dreams of opening other stands like this one.
She even allows herself to imagine making a fortune.
You need to know how to manage.
If you know how to manage your business well,
you can become a millionaire.
If you don't know how to manage it,
you will never be able to become a millionaire.
You must be smart, think hard,
and manage your business well.
But there's still a long way to go,
because Marie's net profit for a day's work is just 15 pounds.
and a third of this sum needs to go to the bank.
towards renting a small apartment with a kitchen on the landing.
This is Fumbwa...
I put peanut butter, garlic, chili, onions and fish in
Inside,
there is a single room,
which is used as a bedroom and living room for Marie and her daughter.
Sarah is the youngest of her five children.
That's Deborah and Israel,
who sat his bac exam today.
With a salary higher than 350 pounds per month,
Marie could live in a bigger apartment.
But she would rather save money on her housing in order to fund her children's studies.
I need to pay for my children's schooling
all on my own.
I had to pay for Deborah and Israel's
in the same year.
You realise I'm paying school fees
for two children at the same time..
...and I still have another daughter Marjorie.
I'm also going to start paying for
Josepha and Jordie, and I'm all alone.
Their schooling costs her 25 pounds per month,
but it will give them the tools they need to encourage them to dream big too.
I could become a millionaire like some people are,
but that will only happen if God wills it.
If he helps me, it will happen.
Like 90%
of Congolese people,
Marie and her daughter Sarah are Christians.
They follow the evangelical denomination.
The shopkeeper visits a temple three times a week.
She thanks God for having spared her from poverty.
God is very important to me.
I have this life thanks to Him.
Evangelical churches thrive in the Congo,
much like in many other African countries.
And by exploiting the Congolese people's strong faith and sometimes their naivety,
some religious leaders have become millionaires.
This Sunday morning in Kinshasa,
all of the city's usually very busy main streets are strangely deserted.
Since dawn,
tens of thousands of people have been heading towards the largest stadium in Central Africa.
Go go go!
You have to go over there.
80,000 attendees are not there for a football match or a huge concert.
They have come to hear a speech from a man who sells a juice,
which supposedly has extraordinary powers.
We always believe in the
prophet Khonde's miracles.
On my deathbed I had a drink, a glass of juice.
And my stomach was like that, greenish,
and it went down straight away.
I am living proof:
he is a prophet, he is a prophet
There are cameramen,
photographers,
cheerleaders.
Policemen on alert.
It's the biggest event of the year.
It is also being broadcast live on television.
The star everyone is waiting for is called The Prophet.
He lives a few kilometers away from the stadium.
We find him at his home where his escort is.
Already ready and dressed impeccably,
his bodyguards are also his disciples.
The prophet Khonde is really a man of God,
one of His messengers..
He really does everything - everything
that Jesus does he does as well.
He is truly our prophet
and God sent him to our country.
The prophet Conde is this man with a floral shirt.
Dominique,
his first name.
created a Christian church in the Congo which has five million followers.
It is a success story that could make people jealous.
Dominique Condé says that he regularly receives death threats.
also
Death threats(al
Death thr
I also have
also have
Death threats
Yes, even
to beat me
to beat me up
Yes, even in Angol
to beat me up, th
Yes, even
to beat me up, they came in with
Yes, even com
to beat me up came-in with guns:
Yes, even in
to beat me up, they came in with
In his living room,
the so-called prophet is proud to show us his dozens of diplomas.
He is recognized as a scientist,
a scholar,
and a universal minister of peace.
He also received the Medal of Civic Merit from the ex-president Joseph Kabila.
He also has a peculiar diploma on display,
which has the European flag on it,
congratulating him for having introduced the juice which delivers and saves.
you a doctor?
doctor?
hat another time,
a lot of headlines
an tell you all that another time,
we can call you; give you a lot of headlines.
that another time,
giveryou a lot of headlines.
I can tell you all that another time,
we can call you, give you a lot of headlines.
all that another time
veryou a lot of headlines.
youall that another time,
u, give you a lot of headlines.
anothertime,
give you a lot of headlines.
tell you all that another time,
ve can call you, give you a lot of headlines.
ere we are more.
The prophet doesn't really respond to the question.
But this supposedly miraculous juice has made him a fortune.
And perhaps that of his church as well.
His first clients are these many loyal followers.
It is 2 o'clock.
Dominique Condé,
surrounded by his armed bodyguards,
leaves for the stadium.
We are here to try and heal those who
are weak, to give advice to the poor.
and heal those who
advice to the poor.
We are here to try and heal those who
are weak, to give advice to the poor.
so that they can live,
ease.
ing difficulty so that they can live,
ven in-famine with ease.
hosefacingdifficult so that they can live,
even in famine, with ease.
ven in famine, with ease.
those facing difficulty so that they can live,
even in-famine,with ease.
Upon arrival,
the man is greeted by a cheering crowd.
Before going on stage,
Dominic Conde greets Bruno Cibala in the crowd,
the country's prime minister.
After prayers and hymns,
the prophet reads his sermon.
They do not want you to succeed, to live in opulence
in abundance, in wealth.
But even in poverty, even if you suffer
from hunger and disease.
From the moment you hold the truth,
you will have everything. Amen my disciples.
Do not fear anything.
Amen my disciples.
The apparent prophet is a clever man.
He does not sell his miraculous juice in public places like this stadium.
He dispenses it more discreetly in small parishes scattered around the country.
It is thanks to this network that he has already raked in millions of pounds.
A few days later,
Dominic Conde holds an open session in Mateta,
in the suburbs of Kinshasa.
There are already more than 100 people waiting on the pavement in front of the entrance for a consultation.
The prophet told me to stop
spending my money in hospitals.
He told me to drink the juice and to pray.
At 11 o'clock,
Dominic Conde arrives in his large 4x4 worth several thousand pounds.
Amen.
Amen Let's eat.
All of his followers have come for his supposedly magical remedy.
But before being allowed to get it,
you must go to the cash register and make a small donation.
Dominic Conde meets a long line of ill people.
I came for the prophet because I am very ill.
I've been ill for years and now I can't even walk.
When I heard about the prophet's work,
I asked to be brought to him.
You have to give her oil and massage it.
You have to massage her with the oil,
that should solve the problem.
have faith that he will succeed in healing me.
Consultations often only last a few seconds.
You need to take the oil juice.
The prescription is always the same.
Are you drinking the juice?
- Yes, I drinki
That's good, you must continue taking it.
Once they've received a prescription,
the ill people are directed towards the room next door,
which is the pharmacy.
This is where you find the famous juice.
It is sold in small used water bottles.
The followers are convinced that it may be a good idea
It even cures AlDs, stomach pain,
liver cancer, cirrhosis, a lot of illnesses.
I had AlDS, I weighed 14kg but now I weigh 52kg.
I was cured of AIDS thanks to the
prophet Khondé's juice.
It's a promise with no scientific foundation,
which can be a dangerous message for ill people.
It costs over 10 pounds for just 500 milliliters of the juice.
It's a huge sum,
which equates to half of the average salary.
As a result,
the poor people of the country
Two or three of us club together
when we don't have much money.
Three of us have come together for it,
so we will share it.
There is lemon, oil, a lot of blending,
we don't really know.
The juice is packed on site.
The demand is so high that Dominic Conde will soon have to begin industrial production.
He has just received the new packaging.
Here are the boxes for the juice.
It mentions on the packaging that it cures diseases such as epilepsy,
cancer,
and even AIDS.
How does it have so much power?
If he could explain,
it would provide a divine inspiration.
But when we ask Dominique Condé to read to us what is written on the box,
he avoids reading the word
This product deals with natural diseases,
such as epilepsy, cancer etc.
It says here that it cures AlDs, but you
didn't mention that one to me.
AIDS, no I haven't marketed it
towards AIDS much.
In the Congo,
around 400,000 people are infected with AIDS.
Another false statement that the prophet gives is that his Jew supposedly resurrects dead children.
Some people give these products to still-
they apply the juice.
...putting it in the still-borns' mouths
and they come back to life.
While we are in his office,
his assistants count and stack banknotes.
This scammer sells tens of thousands of bottles every year and doesn't ever worry about getting caught.